Omar A. Zohdi

Phone: (872) 222-6064 Email: omarzohdi@gmail.com | Website: www.omarzohdi.com | Address: 4010 N Kenmore Ave unit A5, Chicago, IL 60613

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY =

I am a recent graduate from DePaul University, where I completed my MSc in Computer science. I not only see coding as a job but as a passion, I have helped undergraduates learn coding during my time at DePaul as a tutor and I have taken part in multiple programming extra-curricular projects. I focused my academics on learning how to implement large frameworks and optimize the code for ideal performance and faster results. I have had extensive experience mainly in C++/C and C# but also had hands on experience with Java, python and web development languages.

EDUCATION =

DEPAUL UNIVERSITY

Chicago, IL

Master of Science in Computer Science - Computer Game Development

January 2013 – March 2015

- Senior Project: Built a generalized Oculus Rift SDK wrapper for DePaul's Internal Engine, Azul using C++.
- Contributed to the "For the Records" Transmedia Project by developing a JavaScript game.
- Relevant class work includes: Managing Globally Distributed Systems, Game Performance Optimization, Parallel Algorithms, Cognitive Science, and Programming Design Patterns.

UNIVERSITY OF MODERN SCIENCE AND ARTS

Cairo, Egypt

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science

September 2006 – June 2010

- Senior Project: Built a basic 3D Physics framework for Xna using C# including rigid body dynamics and collision detection.
- Relevant class work includes: Software Design Methodology, Computer Networks, Computer Graphics, Multimedia Programming in Java, and Human-Computer Interaction.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

DEPAUL UNIVERSITY

Chicago, Illinois

Graduate Assistant

September 2013 – March 2015

- Taught undergraduate and graduate students how to implement data structures and algorithms.
- Instructed undergraduate students on linear algebra for 3D graphics and gameplay programming courses.
- Assisted gameplay students in learning development best practices in Unity3D and school's internal game engine, Azul.

NAUBA (NEW ENERGY S.R.L.)

Web Developer

Milan, Italy May 2011- August 2012

- Developed multiple e-commerce websites based on client's needs using the Magento framework.
- Worked both as a backend and frontend developer; making use of both client and server side languages including HTML, JavaScript and PHP.
- Contributed to usability design of websites' functionality.

NEW ENERGY S.R.L.

Milan, Italy

IT Consultant

March 2011 - May 2011

- Implemented CRM systems using Oracle Siebel based on clients' needs and iteratively modified and/or added functionality per clients' requests.
- Learned and made use of Oracle Siebel's eScript language to build custom functionality for large pre-existing CRM systems
- Conducted extensive testing and quality assurance of both backend developers' tools and frontend applets functionality for the clients.

- TECHNICAL OVERVIEW AND SKILLS -

DEVELOPMENT TOOLS: Visual studio 2010-2013, Eclipse, NetBeans, and Siebel CRM.

PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES: C++/C, C#, Java, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Python, MySQL and PHP.

APIS & LIBRARIES: OpenGL, LibOVR and OpenCL.

VERSION CONTROL: GitHub, Subversion, and Perforce.

SPOKEN LANGUAGES: Italian, English, and Arabic (Egyptian).

RELEVENT PROJECTS AND CLASSWORK

SOTERIA: DREAMS AS CURRENCY (IN PROGRESS)

C# - Untiy3D

- Oversaw the development of the project as lead programmer at DePaul's serious game lab (Play for Change).
- Defined main code architecture and coordinated with artists for standardized asset pipeline.
- Built multiple systems for the correct structuring of the code.
- Optimized code base for faster and more stable runtime across different platforms.

FOR THE RECORDS – PERFECTION

Silver Medal at International Serious Play Awards 2014

JavaScript

- Determined and constructed game architecture and code design.
- Optimized code for faster and more stable execution across all browsers.
- Iterated through gameplay mechanics with designers input to stay true to the game's message.

CODE OPTIMIZATION

C++

- Wrote and integrated a variable-size and fixed-size block allocator and heap-based memory system in C++, including
 overloading new and delete to provide debug information in select build settings.
- Implemented a load-in-place memory system to remove memory allocation overhead at runtime.
- Optimized a large particle system to increase its speed from more than 1200 ms per update to less than 10 ms.
- Improved cache miss rates in data structures using proper data alignment and padding in classes and structures.

OO DESIGN PATTERNS AND PROGRAMMING

C#

- Made use of more than 10 design patterns in the final project, rendering the code scalable and maintainable.
- Wrote extensive documentation for the code base using C#'s built in documentation features.
- Presented and justified my designs against other students and teacher during the final weeks.

NETWORKING

C# & C++

- Created a network waiting lobby and screen management system to allow for users to join a session, wait for another user to join, leave a waiting room, or leave the session.
- Developed a prediction simulation for debugging purposes to allow for smooth predictive motion (for a mini game the users can take part in) when under constrained bandwidth and latency
- Implemented a serialization/deserialization system to allow data structures of various sizes to be transmitted over a network.